A Guide to the Samuel S. Brooke Papers, 1861-1917
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Samuel S. Brooke Papers, 1861-1917
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00221
The papers consist of eleven items.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Alternative Form
A portion of the Brooke Papers are available in full-text format on the VMI Archives website at: http://www.vmi.edu/archives/manuscripts/ms0221.html
Biographical/Historical Information
Samuel Selden Brooke was born on November 10, 1841 in Stafford County, Virginia, the son of Samuel Selden Brooke, Sr. and Angelina Edrington. Brooke enrolled at the Virginia Military Institute in July 1857 and was a cadet for one year. He subsequently attended the University of Virginia, and in April 1861 he joined the Confederate Army. In May 1861 he was commissioned 2nd Lieutenant, Company I, 47th Virginia Infantry Regiment; in May 1862 he was promoted to Captain. He served with this unit until the end of the Civil War. After the war, Brooke resided in Fredericksburg, Virginia, where he studied law and opened a practice. In 1882 he moved to Roanoke, VA, where he was a newspaper editor and Clerk of Court. He married Bettie Lewis Young in 1872; they had 6 children (Samuel, Henry, Edgar, Vena, Sarah, and Cary). Brooke died January 10, 1918 in Roanoke.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist of five letters, 1862-1864, to and from family members, largely concerned with personal family matters, but with some references to the war and civilian life in Fredericksburg and Richmond, Virginia. Other topics include the 47th Virginia Infantry Regiment, including comments about camp life. In addition to the correspondence, the papers contain commissions, orders, certificates, and miscellaneous official documents dating from Brooke's Civil War service and later life.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1862-1864
  - Letter, 1862 April 17
    From Brooke's sister, writing from Fredericksburg, Virginia. She describes the retreat of the Confederate troops and her fear of the impending occupation of the city by Union troops commanded by Gen. Augur.
  - Letter, 1862 May 17
    From Brooke's aunt, writing from Richmond, VA. Gives Sam the news of his mother's death; laments the "terrible feature of this war that it cuts off all communication with those we love"; family leaving Richmond to go to countryside.
  - Letter, 1862 June 26
    From Brooke's aunt, writing from Fluvanna, VA. Is worried about Sam; mentions family behind enemy lines in Fredericksburg; illness in family; other family concerns.
  - Letter, 1863 August 18
    From Samuel to his sister, writing from the camp of the 47th Virginia Infantry Regiment near Orange Court House, VA. "Marching I do detest and fighting I love no better."
  - Letter, 1864 March 27
    From Samuel to his sister, writing from the camp of the 47th Virginia Infantry Regiment near Orange Court House, VA. "I...do not expect to see you all again until this campaign is over if I am so fortunate as to survive the storm that will soon burst over us."
- Documents, Miscellaneous 1861-1917
  - Commission document, 1861 June 17
  - Special Orders, Number 288, 1864 December 5
    Brooke sent on recruiting trip.
  - Amnesty Oath Document, 1865 June 8
    issued by office of Provost Marshall, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
  - Petition regarding estate of Brooke's father, 1867 March 19
  - Commission document, 1889 May 7
    Appointing Brooke Captain of Roanoke Light Infantry, Virginia Volunteers.
  - United Confederate Veterans document, 1917 October 24